Again, you're going to have to read and tell me which you think is human. Poem 1: Red flags the reason for pretty flags. / And ribbons. Ribbons of flags / And wearing material / Reasons for wearing material. (...) Poem 2: A wounded deer leaps highest, / I've heard the daffodil I've heard the flag to-day / I've heard the hunter tell; / 'Tis but the ecstasy of death, / And then the brake is almost done (...) OK, time is up. So hands up if you think Poem 1 was written by a human. Hands up if you think Poem 2 was written by a human. Whoa, that's a lot more people. So you'd be surprised to find that Poem 1 was written by the very human poet Gertrude Stein. And Poem 2 was generated by an algorithm called RKCP. Now before we go on, let me describe very quickly and simply, how RKCP works. So RKCP is an algorithm designed by Ray Kurzweil, who's a director of engineering at Google and a firm believer in artificial intelligence. So, you give RKCP a source text, it analyzes the source text in order to find out how it uses language, and then it regenerates language that emulates that first text. So in the poem we just saw before, Poem 2, the one that you all thought was human, it was fed a bunch of poems by a poet called Emily Dickinson it looked at the way she used language, learned the model, and then it regenerated a model according to that same structure. But the important thing to know about RKCP is that it doesn't know the meaning of the words it's using. The language is just raw material, it could be Chinese, it could be in Swedish, it could be the collected language from your Facebook feed for one day. It's just raw material. And nevertheless, it's able to create a poem that seems more human than Gertrude Stein's poem, and Gertrude Stein is a human. So what we've done here is, more or less, a reverse Turing test. So Gertrude Stein, who's a human, is able to write a poem that fools a majority of human judges into thinking that it was written by a computer. Therefore, according to the logic of the reverse Turing test, Gertrude Stein is a computer. (Laughter) Feeling confused? I think that's fair enough. So far we've had humans that write like humans, we have computers that write like computers, we have computers that write like humans, but we also have, perhaps most confusingly, humans that write like computers. So what do we take from all of this? Do we take that William Blake is somehow more of a human than Gertrude Stein? Or that Gertrude Stein is more of a computer than William Blake? (Laughter) These are questions I've been asking myself for around two years now, and I don't have any answers. But what I do have are a bunch of insights about our relationship with technology. So my first insight is that, for some reason, we associate poetry with being human. So that when we ask, "Can a computer write poetry?" we're also asking, "What does it mean to be human and how do we put boundaries around this category? How do we say who or what can be part of this category?" This is an essentially philosophical question, I believe, and it can't be answered with a yes or no test, like the Turing test. I also believe that Alan Turing understood this, and that when he devised his test back in 1950, he was doing it as a philosophical provocation. So my second insight is that, when we take the Turing test for poetry, we're not really testing the capacity of the computers because poetry-generating algorithms, they're pretty simple and have existed, more or less, since the 1950s. What we are doing with the Turing test for poetry, rather, is collecting opinions about what constitutes humanness. So, what I've figured out, we've seen this when earlier today, we say that William Blake is more of a human than Gertrude Stein. Of course, this doesn't mean that William Blake was actually more human or that Gertrude Stein was more of a computer. It simply means that the category of the human is unstable. This has led me to understand that the human is not a cold, hard fact. Rather, it is something that's constructed with our opinions and something that changes over time. So my final insight is that the computer, more or less, works like a mirror that reflects any idea of a human that we show it. We show it Emily Dickinson, it gives Emily Dickinson back to us. We show it William Blake, that's what it reflects back to us. We show it Gertrude Stein, what we get back is Gertrude Stein. More than any other bit of technology, the computer is a mirror that reflects any idea of the human we teach it. So I'm sure a lot of you have been hearing a lot about artificial intelligence recently. And much of the conversation is, can we build it? Can we build an intelligent computer? Can we build a creative computer? What we seem to be asking over and over is can we build a human-like computer? But what we've seen just now is that the human is not a scientific fact, that it's an ever-shifting, concatenating idea and one that changes over time. So that when we begin to grapple with the ideas of artificial intelligence in the future, we shouldn't only be asking ourselves, "Can we build it?" But we should also be asking ourselves, "What idea of the human do we want to have reflected back to us?" This is an essentially philosophical idea, and it's one that can't be answered with software alone, but I think requires a moment of species-wide, existential reflection. Thank you. (Applause)
Vous allez à nouveau devoir lire et deviner l'origine du poème. Poème 1 : Drapeaux rouges la raison pour de beaux drapeaux. / Et rubans. Rubans de drapeaux / Et matière portable / Des raisons de porter une matière. (...) Poème 2 : Un cerf blessé saute plus haut,/ J'ai entendu la jonquille J'ai entendu le drapeau ce-jour / J'ai entendu dire le chasseur ; / Ce n'est rien que l'extase de la mort, / Puis le frein est presque rompu. (...) Temps écoulé. Levez la main si vous pensez que le premier est d'un humain. Levez la main si vous pensez que le second est d'un humain. Il y a beaucoup plus de personnes. Vous serez surpris d'apprendre que le premier poème a été écrit par la poètesse humaine Gertrude Stein. Et le second poème a été généré par l'algorithme RKCP. Avant de continuer, je vais décrire rapidement et simplement le fonctionnement de RKCP. RKCP est un algorithme créé par Ray Kurzweil, qui est directeur de l'ingénierie chez Google et un fervent croyant en l'intelligence artificielle. Vous donnez un texte source à RKCP, il analyse le texte source afin de comprendre l'utilisation du langage, ensuite il régénère un langage qui imite ce premier texte. Le poème que nous venons de voir, le second, qui était, selon vous, écrit par un humain, a été nourri par un lot de poèmes de la poètesse Emily Dickinson. Il a analysé son utilisation du langage, a appris le modèle, puis généré un modèle suivant la même structure. Ce qu'il est important de savoir sur RKCP est qu'il ne connaît pas le sens des mots qu'il emploie. La langue est une matière première, cela pourrait être du chinois, du suédois, ou encore les mots collectés sur votre fil d'actualités Facebook du jour. C'est une matière première. Et pourtant, il est capable de créer un poème qui semble plus humain que celui de Gertrude Stein, et Gertude Stein est humaine. Ce que nous avons fait est plus ou moins un test de Turing inversé. Gertrude Stein, qui est humaine, est capable d'écrire un poème qui fait croire à la majorité des juges humains qu'il a été écrit par un ordinateur. Ainsi, selon la logique inverse du test de Turing, Gertrude Stein est un ordinateur. (Rires) Vous êtes perdus ? Je pense que c'est normal. Jusqu'ici nous avons eu des humains écrivant comme des humains, des ordinateurs écrivant comme des ordinateurs, des ordinateurs écrivant comme des humains, mais nous avons aussi, et c'est le plus déroutant, des humains écrivant comme des ordinateurs. Que tirons-nous de cela ? Que William Blake est, d'une façon, plus humain que Gertrude Stein ? Ou que Gertrude Stein est plus ordinateur que William Blake ? (Rires) Ce sont les questions que je me pose depuis environ deux ans, et je n'ai aucune réponse. Mais j'ai eu différents aperçus de notre relation à la technologie. La première chose est que, pour une raison quelconque, nous associons à la poésie au fait d'être humain. Donc quand nous demandons si un ordinateur peut écrire de la poésie, nous demandons également la signification du fait d'être humain et comment délimiter cette catégorie. Comment dire qui ou quoi fait partie de cette catégorie ? C'est une question essentiellement philosophique qui n'admet pas une réponse grâce à un test binaire, comme le test de Turing. Je pense qu'Alan Turing comprenait cela quand il a conçu son test en 1950, c'était une provocation philosophique. La seconde chose est que, en passant le test de Turing pour la poésie, nous ne testons pas la capacité des ordinateurs, les algorithmes générant de la poésie sont simples et existent depuis les années 50. Ce que nous faisons est plutôt de collecter des opinions sur la signification de l'humanité. J'ai découvert que, nous l'avons vu plus tôt, nous disions que William Blake est plus humain que Gertrude Stein. Bien sûr, cela ne veut pas dire que William Blake est vraiment plus humain ou que Gertrude Stein est plus un ordinateur. Cela signifie que la catégorie de l'humain est instable. Cela m'a permis de comprendre que l'humanité n'est pas une vérité rigide. Mais est plutôt quelque chose qui se construit avec nos opinions et qui évolue dans le temps. Finalement, je pense qu'un ordinateur fonctionne plus ou moins comme un miroir qui reflète l'idée de l'humain que nous lui montrons. Nous lui montrons Emily Dickinson, il nous rend Emily Dickinson. Nous lui montrons William Blake, il nous le reflète en retour. Nous lui montrons Gertrude Stein, nous récupérons Gertrude Stein. Plus que toute technologie, l'ordinateur est un miroir qui reflète l'idée de l'humanité que nous lui inculquons. Nombre d'entre vous ont dû récemment entendre parler énormément d'intelligence artificielle. Et le cœur de la conversation est : pouvons-nous la créer ? Pouvons-nous créer un ordinateur intelligent ? Pouvons-nous créer un ordinateur créatif ? Ce que nous demandons sans cesse est : pouvons-nous créer un ordinateur ressemblant à un humain ? Nous venons de voir que l'humanité n'est pas un fait scientifique, que c'est une concaténation d'idées qui change et évolue perpétuellement avec le temps. Quand nous commençons à débattre de l'idée d'une intelligence artificielle dans le futur, nous ne devrions pas juste nous demander si nous pouvons la créer mais nous devrions nous demander quelle idée de l'humain nous voulons refléter. C'est une idée essentiellement philosophique, qui ne peut trouver de réponse avec juste un logiciel mais qui requiert un moment de réflexion existentielle de notre part à tous. Merci. (Applaudissements)